We hooked a big fish for today's episode
as NFL Network's Daniel Jeremiah joins
the show. DJ, welcome in. The reason we
have you here is to talk some NFL draft,
but before we get into that, I want to
start with the big move of free agency
for the Miami Dolphins here with
quarterback Malik Willis. And man, what
a fun tape it was to watch him going all
the way back to Liberty. And I was
wondering if you off the top of your
head, DJ, I know you're so good at doing
this, can like think back to your Malik
Willis scouting report out of Liberty
four years ago and what you remember
most about him as a prospect. Well, I
remember the raw part of it, right? Like
it was not, you know, pristine clean,
but I remember just thinking he has so
much juice in his arm and he's got so
much juice in his legs. Like he is just
he just twitch twitch twitch, you know,
all over the place. So big time power
throws, you know, dynamic explosive
runner. Um, so you had the uh, you know,
it was a it was definitely a little bit
of a roller coaster ride because it
wasn't always the way you would dial it
up or coach it up, but you could see the
raw physical traits that he had and he
was super competitive. U, so those are
the things I remember on the field and
then having a chance, as fate would have
it, I sat next to him on a flight on the
way to the combine. Um, either way or or
leaving. Anyways, I was I sat I was on
next to him for an entire flight and got
to really know the guy and uh what a
good dude. What a really really good
dude. So excited to see him get that
opportunity after Tennessee to go to
Green Bay and and uh and really flourish
in the limited opportunities there and
now to land with some guys who are
familiar with him. Yeah, that seems to
be the the kind of personal scouting
report on him is just how like humble
and and kind of grounded he is. And that
I picked that up meeting him here for
the first day he was on campus with us.
And I think the follow-up to that
question, DJ, is pretty natural because,
you know, he goes the two years in
Tennessee and then goes to Green Bay and
gets with Matt Laflur, right? A really
good quarterback whisperer. And what do
you think that did for his development?
Like I I mean, this is a guy that's the
same age as Tyler Shuck and Bo Nicks.
Like he's he's got a lot of football
ahead of him. And I think the Green Bay
tape was was pretty good, too.
>> Yeah, it was really good. You know,
obviously the sample size is small, but
I thought he played more decisive, like
he just trusted what he was seeing,
trusting the picture and then letting it
rip or, you know, using his legs and
going out and making something happen. I
think when you're a young player, I
think sometimes the picture can be a
little bit fuzzy. You don't have, you
know, the confidence that you're seeing
it the way you need to see it to let it
rip. And I thought that had cleared up
for him. And some of that is his growth.
Some of that is designing an offense,
you know, to make him comfortable and to
clear up some things for him vision
wise. And um you know that's going to be
the challenge is can you can you do that
now in a place where you're not going to
have all the pieces there that you had
in Green Bay initially. Now we'll see
what they can accomplish here in the
draft. But um you know he's he's going
to chance to be the guy and and I think
you're going to see him grow you know
throughout the year. You'll see a guy
week one and week two. I think you're
going to see a better version as we go
throughout the year. Week eight, week
nine and as you as you go forward but
they've got a lot of stuff they need to
add here uh as we get towards uh draft
season. Finally, some draft talk here
for you, DJ. Pick 11, the first pick of
the John Eric Sullivan era, and he's
he's preached toughness, love of the
game, and he talked about how it starts
with the quarterback. Check that box off
right there. He's talked about building
this team inside out. We've got Jeff
Hafley who's cut his teeth as DB's coach
in this league. What's your lean on some
good fits for the Dolphins at pick
number 11 right now?
>> Yeah, there's a lot of different ways
they can go. And I know, you know, they
took Golden in the first round, but they
had not been a first round wide receiver
organization in Green Bay where they,
you know, were kind of forged. But when
you look at them having a need after the
Wadd trade and you look at if you're
looking to add competitive, you know,
feisty, tough players like a Mai Lemon
comes into that mix for me at that point
in time. You look outside at the corner
position, Mansour Delane, you know, is a
really, really rock solid player who's
got as consistent a tape as anybody in
this year's draft class. I mean, there's
those are two ways to to plug holes
right there. We'll see what happens, you
know, with the pass rushers. I I think
those big three are probably gone, but
if Bane were to be there, um that's kind
of a tone setter player that uh brings
an identity and a toughness and u you
know, a real competitiveness to that
group. That to me is the trait that I'm
I'm keeping an eye on. That to me feels
like what it is more so than inside out
or what positions they prioritize. To
me, it's about the identity that they're
trying to present. And that's, you know,
whether you're taking a receiver, a
corner, a dtackle, an edge rusher, um,
that's what I'm looking for from this
group. I would imagine they're going to
try and go find somebody that's ultra
ultra competitive and wired the right
way.
>> I love Omar Cooper Jr. for instance,
from Indiana and I went and read your
top 50 and you have him at 18. I'm like,
maybe the dream at 30 might be dead
there because he checks those boxes you
just talked about, man. So, is that kind
of a spot where you think he could go or
is he going to be long gone by the time
the Dolphins pick at number 30? I'd be
surprised if he got to 30, but you know,
because of the need at the tackle
position around the league, you could
see a lot of these tackles go, which
means somebody's got to fall. Um, and
maybe, you know, because we have some
receiver depth that, you know, that
could push some of those guys down
there. Be a heck of a pick. I mean, I I
love the way he plays the game and not
only the way he can go attack the ball
and, you know, you can work in the
middle of the field, but just after the
catch, like he just he refuses to be
tackled. Um, I I think there's an edge
to his game and obviously, you know, the
clutch factor is there if you watch the
Penn State game winner. So, he's he's
someone that's uh I I I would I would be
jumping up and down high-fiving the
entire draft room if he's there at 30.
>> Um, I I guess I want to stay there, DJ,
because I guess this has become the
receiver podcast because we have a bunch
of picks, seven in the top 100 here, and
I keep hearing about the the size guys,
like the the bigger body receivers in
that second and third round, the second
day of the draft. Who are some guys you
like in that range for Miami?
>> Well, I mean, we'll see where Denzel
Boston ends up going. Um, I think he was
a I thought he was a first round type
player, but I think he more than likely
lands in the second round uh when it's
all said and done. Malachi Fields did
not run as well as he would have liked
out of Notre Dame. I think he's
somewhere on day two in that mix. Uh, I
like him a lot as a player. If you want,
you know, more of a downfield guy, you
know, you start talking about Ted Hurst
who could fill that role uh as as a
vertical player out of Georgia State.
There's going to be a lot of intriguing
options uh in in that in that world. So,
I'm I'm excited about that. Day two two
clump of wide receivers. Um Bell from
Louisville coming off the injury is
going to be a value pick for somebody on
day two. So, a lot of good options if
you're looking for those bigger guys.
>> Yeah, I'll go ahead and close the show
the way we started here. DJ talking
about some team building concepts
because, you know, seven picks in the
top 100, two in the first round. I was
hoping you could kind of take us into
your days inside NFL draft rooms on this
thought because we've now got picks 87,
90, and 94. That's three out of seven.
Does that change a team's approach at
all when you own nearly 40% of a seven
pick clump in the draft like that?
>> Well, it it makes things easy because
usually you're you're sweating it out
and then you're having that look up at
the board of like, okay, we got three
guys we like. You know who, you know,
which one of these guys are we going to
get? And it's literally a cake and eat
it too situation of like we're going to
get we can get all of them. Like now
it's just the the matter of what order
we want to rip them off the board
because the little gap in between are we
going to get hung out to dry. So I would
imagine they will they will do their
homework on the teams in that clump uh
there with them and the teams behind
them that could jump them. So uh they're
going to have an opportunity to get
three really good players there. And
also, you're in a position where if you
could pick up some some draft capital in
27 and maybe spin off one of those
picks, that's an option. You know, as
the trade market continues to develop,
you know, after the draft is another
time where after teams have kind of
doubled up on some areas of their
roster, you could be uh, you know, you
could be in a situation where if you can
get some extra picks for next year, you
could you could trade for veterans as
well. So, there's there's an infinite
number of options there with all those
picks.
>> That did happen last year. They moved
off a fourth round pick last year for a
third round pick this year. So, one of
the many they have in their war chest
here of draft pick. Stay on Jeremiah is
the host of the Move the Sticks podcast
and the 40s and free agents podcast.
Both of which are available wherever you
listen to your podcast. DJ, thanks for
your time today, man. Go Mariners, go
Padres's and we'll see you again next
time, man.
>> Yeah, looking forward to it. Happy
baseball season, happy draft season. The
Masters, the tournament. It is the best
time of the year.
We are back in the film room here on
Dolphins HQ and we've talked a lot about
Jeff Hafley's defense and what it might
look like in terms of structure and
design. Now, we're going to tell you
about how some of the pieces might fit
in terms of Dolphins personnel in that
defense. Let's go ahead and talk about
Chop going back to 2024 right here in a
position that more suits him in my
opinion in this defense off the edge at
the wide nine technique. You're going to
get a chip from the tight end right
here. The tackle's going to try to pick
him up. Neither is going to work and
he's going to sack Drake May on this
play back in 2024 against the New
England Patriots. So, the wide nine
technique. Go ahead and swipe the end,
get under the tackle, and finish at the
quarterback right there. This is really,
I mean, the ideal look for Chop Robinson
rushing the quarterback. Get him plenty
of runway here. Look at all the space he
has to operate with. This tight end
can't chip him. Going to go ahead and
throw him to the side. And then watch
the way he dips under the right tackle.
Whoop! Right under him and to the
quarterback. That is the type of
explosion that you draft this guy for.
and the runway to create for him to give
him the path to get to the quarterback
that directly. A big time dip and uh
drop there at the quarterback. We're
going to show you how Kenneth Grant
helped make this play happen. Right
here, he's playing a two eye off the
inside shoulder of the guard and he can
play out here at the three technique off
the outside shoulder. He can play all
over your defensive line, but I want to
show you these clips of him working
inside as a pass rusher where he can
really help impact this Jeff Halfley
rush plan when it comes to creating
pressure on quarterbacks. So once again,
this is John Simpson, who's a really
good guard for the New York Jets. Watch
how quickly Kenneth Grant dispatches him
on this pass rush. Go ahead and use the
hands to swipe the punch and then dip
around the inside. He has got all kinds
of athletic ability, side to side,
agility to force the quarterback off the
spot. And that's what we're looking at
here from the two-ey technique position
as a pass rusher to get a sack here on a
critical stop for this Dolphins defense.
Let's go ahead and jump ahead to a play
on the Packers defense and show you a
little bit of how all those things just
kind of show you how Jeff Hafley can
utilize Chop Robinson, Kenneth Grant,
Zack Cer, Jordan Brooks, all the big
time names in the Dolphins front and
create pressure on opposing
quarterbacks. We're going to see a
Jacobe Brassette sack here for this
Packers defense with Michael Parsons,
Quay Walker, Carl Brooks, and show you
the end zone angle here to show you how
it comes together. So Kenneth Grant
playing that two-ey technique. That's
Carl Brooks right there. Quay Walker is
going to walk up into the A gap here and
mug up and rush the quarterback. And
Micah Parson's going to kick out wide
and rush that wide nine technique. So
think about Chop, think about KG, think
about Jordan Brooks in that position.
And it's going to result in a sack here
on Cardinals quarterback Jacobe
Brassette. So watch the way Carl Brooks
threatens this a gap and widens the path
for Qua Walker. Get a double team right
there. Create that free run on the
running back to pick him up. He can't do
that either. And watch the way Michael
Parsons angles around the corner here to
put pressure on the quarterback. All the
escape hatches there for Jacobe Briseta
have been taken away and it results in a
sack on that Packers defense. So all
those parts kind of fit together. Let's
go ahead and jump ahead to this clip
here of some Dolphins defensive backs
and focus on this one on Guju Brent,
Julius Brent who was picked up last
September off the waiver wire and watch
this coverage rep. The tape kind of
speaks for itself here against Keon
Coleman. He is all over him on multiple
moves outside of structure right here.
Winds up getting a PBU. has a fantastic
rep from a quarterback that is fast, is
physical, is long, he has good change of
direction skill set. There's the inside
hand jam. When see that little punch
right there on the inside shoulder that
gets Keon Coleman off of his balance and
gets him to kind of reroute and then he
gets right into phase. That's a great
position to be in as a quarterback. He
runs up field, cuts back, change of
direction, click and close, all the
scouting terms you want to hear about.
He showed really, really good skill sets
there in terms of coverage to get the
PBU on that particular play. Another
player that I like in this Dolphins
defensive backfield is Jason Marshall
Jr. playing a slot position right here.
And this is going to be a coverage
inversion. What that means, you're going
to get quarterbacks peeling out and
safety stepping down to invert the way
the coverage operates. And to be totally
honest, I'm not sure if this is cover
two, if it's cover six. It could be
either of those because the variations
are kind of similar, but I think you're
in a quarter quarter half situation
right here with Jack Jones, Jason
Marshall Jr., and this safety is your
quarter quarter half players. But what I
want you to watch is the way Jason
Marshall gets out and sprints
vertically. That's the long speed, the
change of direction, flip the hips, and
then this ball comes in from Baker
Mayfield with really good timing because
this player has his hips turned. He's
running vertical. We're going to try to
jam this thing into the seam right here.
But watch the put the foot in the
ground. Jason Marshall plants the foot
in the ground, drives back downhill, and
makes a play. That is really heady play
to kind of do your responsibility, do
your job, and then flip back downhill
and go make a play somewhat outside of
the job responsibility to react to a
pretty good throw from the quarterback
right there. I'll go ahead and show you
one more clip here of the Packers
defense doing something similar where
they're going to blitz the quarterback,
find a way to get pressure on Dak
Prescott here, and then put their
quarterback on an island on this target
out here against George Pickkins. The
Cowboys, you could say best receiver. CD
lands pretty good, too. They got two
good options, but right here, man
coverage against this outside
cornerback, press, kind of mirror the
coverage, run up field, get vertical,
and force the incompletion on that
particular route. So, this defense has
all kinds of variation, all kinds of
structure, different ways to create
pressure, and this young Dolphins core
has a good chance to fulfill what Jeff
Hathley's defense needs right away here
in 2026.